Lawrence Lariar Papers
Lawrence Lariar Papers
1926-1965
1942-1954
Lariar, Lawrence, 1908-1981
2 linear ft.
Original cartoons, sketches, book and magazine illustrations, writings, scripts, correspondence, scrapbooks, clippings and published material (including biographical material).
2655690
Biographical History
Lawrence Lariar (1908-1981) was an American cartoonist, illustrator and writer.
Born in Brooklyn, New York, Lariar graduated from Erasmus High School in 1925 and studied art at the New York School of Fine and Applied Arts (1926-1929). Later, he studied at the Academie Julien in Paris and at the Art Students League of New York. Initially he worked as a commercial advertising artist, but after 1933 he shifted his focus to freelance illustration and cartooning. His work often appeared in the New York daily papers, as well as popular magazines of the era including Saturday Evening Post, Collier's, American Magazine, College Humor, New Yorker, Judge, and Country Gentlemen. He was cartoon editor of Liberty Magazine (1941-1948) and of Parade magazine. He served as Director of the Professional School of Cartooning and as President of the American Society of Magazine Cartoonists. Lariar authored and edited numerous books over the course of his career including the annual series Best Cartoons of the Year. He also published mystery novels under the names Adam Knight, Michael Stark and Michael Lawrence.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lawrence Lariar Papers consists of artwork, correspondence, memorabilia, and writings. In some cases material arrived with notes from Lariar giving explanations or dates; these notes have been retained with the material in the appropriate folders.
Artwork contains both published and original work. Original art contains drawings for the books Andrew the Ant and Golf and Be Damned, as well as greeting cards, assorted cartoons and sketches, and a self-caricature. Published material includes cartoons published in both magazines and newspapers as well as advertising art, several comic strips, and a few political cartoons. In some cases it was impossible to tell whether the title at the top of the page was the title of the cartoon or the title of the publication in which it appeared, so all are alphabetized together. Many of the published cartoons were published during World War II and have military life as their theme.
Correspondence contains general correspondence as well as a separate folder relating to Lariar's work with the USO, the Committee on War Cartoons, and other war efforts.
Writings contains published material (articles, the dust jackets for two of Lariar's books, humor pieces, and short stories) and manuscripts (typescript of Andrew the Ant, the short story "Flatbush is a horrible place," and a television script for Rocky King, Detective.
Memorabilia contains clippings about Lariar, two scrapbooks of Lariar's cartoons and humorous writings, and clippings from the "Colonel Stoopnagle's Scrapbook" humor page.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has more than 40 published works by, or edited by, Lawrence Lariar in our Rare Books holdings. Please consult for additional information.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Lariar, Lawrence, 1908-1981.; American wit and humor.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Humorous stories, American.; Illustrations -- United States.; Illustrators -- United states.; Soldiers -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Military life -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Illustrations.; Scripts (documents); Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lawrence Lariar, 1967, 1969-1970, 1977.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Original art
    - Andrew the Ant book illustrations, book illustrations (Oversize 1)
    - Cartoons, miscellaneous, 1965; undated (Oversize 1)
    - Golf and be Damned, undated; book illustrations (Oversize 1)
    - Greeting cards, undated; most are military-themed Christmas cards (Box 1)
    - Self-caricature, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926; 1927,; 1936,; 1938; political cartoon, sketch of centaur labeled as "done while working on Walt Disney's Fantasia" (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1927; 1929,; undated; includes student drawing (age 18), cover art for Best Cartoons of 1945 (Oversize 1)
  - Printed material
    - Advertisements, 1943; undated (Oversize 1)
    - Cartoons
      - "...And so it goes!", 1937 (Oversize 1)
      - Army Daze, undated (Box 1)
      - College Life, undated (Box 1)
      - Collier's, 1948; undated (Box 1)
      - Fun Riot, undated (Box 1)
      - "The Home Front", undated; includes parody entitled "Shirt Front," an advertisement for a shirt company (Box 1)
      - Hooey, undated (Box 1)
      - "Laffs by Lariar", 1935; 1936 (Box 1)
      - "Manual of War," no's 4, 5, and 6, undated (Box 1)
      - Parade Magazine, 1964 (Box 1)
      - Saturday Evening Post, undated (Box 1)
      - Squad's Riot, undated (Box 1)
      - "This and That", 1941-1942 (Box 1)
      - Whiz Bang, undated (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1929; 1943-1944,; undated; clippings from magazines and newspapers; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Comic strips
      - The Bantam Prince, undated; press kit, including sample strips (Oversize 1)
      - Barry O'Neill, 1934 (Oversize 1)
      - Ben Friday, 1950; press kit, including sample strips (Oversize 1)
      - Inspector Keene of Scotland Yard, undated; includes clipping of published fan letter (Box 1)
      - Samson the Cop, 1928; Lariar's first attempt at a comic strip; proofs (Box 1)
    - Political cartons, circa 1941-1945; includes cartoons relating to World War II, political figures and parties, cartoons featuring soldiers and sailors (Box 1)
    - Political cartons, 1937; 1942-1944,; undated; includes cartoons relating to World War II, political figures and parties, cartoons featuring soldiers and sailors (Oversize 1)
- Correspondence
  - War effort, 1943-1945; undated; includes correspondence, photographs of USO visit, a few printed cartoons (Box 1)
  - General, 1936; 1942-1945,; 1950,; 1953-1954,; 1964 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings about, 1941-1946; 1949-1957,; 1962 (Oversize 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Cartoon clippings, undated; bound volume (Oversize 2)
    - Cartoon clippings, undated; cartoons published in Collier's, Saturday Evening Post, other magazines (Oversize 2)
    - "Colonel Stoopnagle's Scrapbook", 1946; clippings of full-page humor feature; one bound volume, several loose pages (Oversize 2)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts
    - Andrew the Ant, undated; children's book; typescript withe extensive notes and corrections (Box 1)
    - "Flatbush is a horrible place", undated; short story; typescript (Box 1)
    - Rocky King, Detective television script, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Published
    - Articles, 1945; 1951,; 1952,; undated; includes "Morale literature: its part in rehabilitation" on cartoons and soldiers (Box 1)
    - Book jackets, 1944; undated; The Man with the Lumpy Nose (mystery novel by Lariar) and Best Cartoons of the Year (edited and cover art by Lariar) (Box 1)
    - Humor pieces, undated; includes several humorous essays illustrated with 19th century photographs (Box 1)
    - Letter to the editor, 1945; rebuttal of negative review of Lariar's Best Cartoons of 1945 (Box 1)
    - Short stories, 1945; 1949,; 1957,; undated; clippings from various magazines (Oversize 2)